Guide to the William Blake Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Blake collection
1780-1957
1780-1834
GEN MSS 914
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
The collection consists of documents, correspondence, and drawings by the English artist William Blake and his colleague John Linnell. Included are business and financial documents covering the relationship between Blake and Linnell, a letter from Blake to Linnell, two drawings by Blake, and a portrait of Blake by Linnell. The items were acquired by the library between 1941 and 1973.
Blake, William, 1757-1827
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection of documents was acquired by gift and purchase from various sources between 1941 and 1973. Source information is recorded at the folder level in the contents list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Blake (1757-1827)
English artist and poet.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of documents, correspondence, and drawings by the English artist William Blake and his colleague John Linnell. Included are business and financial documents covering the relationship between Blake and Linnell, a letter from Blake to Linnell, two drawings by Blake, and a portrait of Blake by Linnell. The items were acquired by the library between 1941 and 1973.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Documents Related to the Book of Job, 1819-1941. II. Other Papers, 1780-1957.
Artists -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Account books -- England -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- England -- 18th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- England -- 18th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Blake, William, 1757-1827; Linnell, John, 1792-1882
- Documents Related to the Book of Job, 1819-1941; Series I; 6
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Otis T. Bradley (Yale 1915), 1941.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of a group of papers documenting the financial and business relationship of William Blake and John Linnell. The items are fully described in "New Blake Documents" by Geoffrey Keynes ( Times Literary Supplement, January 9, 1943) and in Blake Studies: Notes on His Life and Work, in Seventeen Chapters, by Geoffrey Keynes (London, R. Hart-Davis, 1949).
  - Typed inventory and description of documents, circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript memorandum of agreement between John Linnell and William Blake, written by Linnell and signed by Blake, 1823 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Subscribers & Purchasers of the Book of Illustrations of the History of Job Designed & Engraved by William Blake", 1823-1834 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    General note
    Two small autograph manuscript account books pasted together, containing approximately 10 pages of notes by Blake, with some later entries in another hand
  - Accounts of money paid to William Blake by John Linnell, 1824-1825 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Four autograph manuscript pages (on three leaves) of accounts paid for "The Portrait of Mr Lowry," "sketches of subjects from Dante," "drawings of Paradise regained," and "on account of Job"
  - Receipts for money paid to William Blake by John Linnell, 1819-1826 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Ten autograph manuscript receipts signed by William Blake and one signed by Frederick Tatham for Blake, which span the relationship of Blake and Linnell. The receipts are regarding help with Mr. Upton's portrait, and for Songs of Innocence and Experience, Jerusalem, Heaven and Hell, The Book of Job, and other accounts
  - Bespoke leather case by Riviere and Son that formerly held the Bradley documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Other Papers, 1780-1957; Series II; 5
  The series consists of two letters and three drawings.
  - Autograph manuscript letter, signed, from William Blake to an unidentified recipient, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1973.
    Published in "A Blake Letter Found," by G. E. Bentley, Jr., in Yale University Library Gazette 68, no. ½ (October 1993): 60-64.
  - Autograph manuscript letter, signed, from William Blake to John Linnell, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Purchased from Alfred W. Van Sinderen (Yale 1945) on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Fund, 1965.
    Formerly laid in Blake's Songs of Innocence, copy Q; see Keynes and Wolf, William Blake's Illuminated Books (New York, 1953), 16-17.
  - Drawing, "The Keys of Calais," by William Blake; watercolor and ink on paper, circa 1780, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift of Robert J. Barry in memory of Louis M. Rabinowitz, 1957.
    Drawing 12.5 x 18 cm. mounted on a card 35 x 39 cm. Accompanied by typed description and exhibition history prepared by C. A. Stonehill, Inc.
  - Drawing, "Timon," by William Blake and John Linnell; watercolor, ink, and graphite on paper, circa 1798 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Gift of Alfred W. Van Sinderen (Yale 1945), 1965.
    Drawing measures 11.5 x 13.5 cm. Formerly laid in Blake's Songs of Innocence, copy Q; see Keynes and Wolf, William Blake's Illuminated Books (New York, 1953), 16.
    Martin Butlin (Tate Gallery) examined the drawing on June 6, 1966, and said that it is "possibly a working over, by Linnell, of a pencil and wash drawing by Blake." Butlin identified the inscriptions on the drawing, "Timon" and "By Wm Blake," as Linnell's handwriting.
  - Profile portrait of William Blake, by John Linnell; ink on paper, signed., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Drawing measures 16.5 x 11.5 cm. Formerly laid in Blake's Songs of Innocence, copy Q; see Keynes and Wolf, William Blake's Illuminated Books (New York, 1953), 16-17.